Hello everyone, and welcome!
I'm Dr. Michael Greger,
coming to you live from my stationary
treadmill. Just so I don't make people
seasick back on the East Coast—my
Vancouver move did not last very long.
This is a CME-approved webinar, meaning
Continuing Medical Education for doctors
and other medical professionals. As you can
see, I am proud to declare I have no relevant
financial relationships with ineligible
companies to disclose. That’s the kind of
declaration statement that’s necessary
given the long, checkered past of Big
Pharma secretly propping up paid shills to push
their products. So now they just not-so-secretly
prop up paid shills to push their
products. But I am not one of them.
Okay, if at any time you run into technical
difficulties, there are live chatroom staff
standing by. Let me paste that link into the
chat—boom, there we go. And if they are unable
to help you, we have NutritionFacts.org staff
also standing by. Let me paste that into the
chat box as well. This is your donations hard at
work supporting the nonprofit NutritionFacts.org.
All right, please reserve the Q&A button you see
for content questions, as opposed to technical
questions. Today’s webinar is two hours with a
pee break on the hour, but I’ve reserved lots
of time for Q&A at the end, so please feel
free to add questions using the Q&A button
throughout the webinar. Then the NutritionFacts
team will compile them to be answered at the end.
You don’t have to worry about taking notes
or anything. After the webinar’s over,
we’re not only going to send you a full
recording of it but also a free link to
download all the videos in high-def so you can
see the videos in their full-resolution glory.
Okay, let’s do this! Today we are going to
be talking about all things NAD, which stands
for nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide.
If I can’t start pronouncing this now,
it’s going to be a long webinar:
nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide,
which is an essential cofactor for
hundreds of enzymes within the body,
including a purported anti-aging enzyme. Raising
levels can extend lifespan and rejuvenate
health in a variety of animals. What about in
humans? That’s what we’re going to talk about.
The four main NAD-boosting supplements
on the market are nicotinamide riboside,
also known as NR; nicotinamide mononucleotide,
also known as NMN; nicotinic acid;
and nicotinamide. In this two-hour webinar, I
will cover the pros and cons of each of those,
as well as the other five NAD-boosting
supplements on the market. I’ll also
discuss three ways to naturally boost NAD
levels without taking any supplements at all.
Let’s begin with a video that
lays out what exactly NAD
is and asks the question: do
NAD levels decline with age?
Our understanding of nicotinamide
adenine dinucleotide (NAD+)
arose from humble beginnings as a factor
noted to enhance yeast fermentation
in a 1906 paper unassumingly entitled
“The Alcoholic Ferment of Yeast-Juice.”
Little did they know that
waves of NAD-related discoveries
would go on to yield a
total of four Nobel Prizes.
NAD+ is now known as an essential
molecule for all living organisms,
required for the function
of about 500 enzymes,
including, notably, the extraction
of metabolic energy from food.
The 21st century has produced yet
another scientific renaissance for NAD+
with the realization that it was
critical for the activity of sirtuins,
the “guardians of mammalian healthspan”
I detail in my book, How Not to Age.
NAD+ is one of the most abundant
molecules in our body.
Once considered relatively stable,
it’s now known to be in a constant state
of synthesis, recycling, and breakdown.
The entire pool of NAD+
in some of our tissues
is turned over
several times a day.
To maintain cellular vitality
in the face of this turnover,
an adequate supply
of NAD+ precursors
and sufficiently high enzyme activity
synthesizing NAD+ are critical.
The importance of NAD+ is exemplified
by the devastating consequences
of a deficiency of NAD+ precursors
like niacin (vitamin B3).
The deficiency syndrome,
called pellagra,
is characterized by the 4 D’s:
dermatitis, dementia, diarrhea,
and, eventually, death.
Thankfully, since life as we know
it couldn’t exist without it,
NAD+ and its precursors are
found in everything we eat—
plant, animal, or fungi—
but we need to know
how to get at them.
The niacin in corn, for instance,
is tightly bound up,
but it can be released by pre-
soaking in alkaline lime-water.
Maize was exported
from Latin America
to become a dietary staple
without the requisite knowledge
about traditional processing
techniques, though,
and an epidemic
of pellagra ensued.
An estimated 100,000 Americans
died from pellagra
in the first few decades
of the 20th century
before bread started to be
fortified with niacin in 1938.
The pitch for NAD+ boosting as an
anti-aging strategy goes as follows:
all species,
including humans,
naturally experience a decline
in NAD+ levels over time,
and this decline is, in fact,
one of the major
reasons organisms age.
By restoring youthful levels,
the argument goes,
these age-related disorders can
be delayed or even reversed.
Two leaders in the field,
one from Harvard and the other MIT,
have said, respectively,
that NAD+ boosters may
“hold the promise of increasing
the body’s resilience,
not just to one disease,
but to many,
thereby extending healthy
human lifespan,”
and that sirtuin activation
by NAD+ repletion
“may be the most actionable item
to emerge from aging research.”
Of course, they have
both been involved
in multimillion-dollar dietary
supplement companies.
The first premise, that NAD+
levels decline with age,
has been called into question.
For example,
this 2022 review
“Age-Dependent Decline of NAD+—
Universal Truth or Confounded Consensus?”
concluded that, despite
systemic claims to the contrary,
the evidence supporting
the premise is very limited.
Indeed, the most
comprehensive study to date
found significant changes
in NAD+ levels
in less than half of the tested
tissues in old versus young mice.
The human data are
similarly inconsistent.
NAD+ boosting supplement
shills make claims like
“By middle age,
our NAD+ levels
have plummeted to half
that of our youth,”
but the cited source only shows a
drop (in brain levels) of about 13%
between about
the ages 20 to 60.
A similar study estimated about
an 18% drop from age 25 to 70,
both broadly consistent with a
14% drop in spinal tap fluid samples
taken from those over
age 45 (average age 71),
compared to those under
age 45 (average age 34).
It’s unclear if such modest differences
would have any consequences,
and a more recent study found
no significant differences at all
in brain nor muscle levels between
a young group (average age 21)
and an older group
(average age 69).
A study of skin samples found a greater
than 50% drop in young adults
compared to the skin of newborns,
and a further drop of about 60%
from young adults to middle age.
However, there did not seem to be
a further decline from middle to old age.
There was a small study that found
the NAD+ levels in the liver samples
of six older individuals
(average age 66)
was about 30% lower than that of
six younger individuals (average age 39).
NAD+ levels also may
be lower in macrophage
white blood cells
in older individuals,
but in the blood more generally,
half the studies showed
a decline with age,
and the other half didn’t.
By far the largest study
(enrolling 10 times more people
than the other studies combined)
found a slight drop in NAD+
in the aging bloodstreams
of men but no drop in women.
The bottom line is that,
given the conflicting results from the
remarkably few studies on the subject,
it’s misleading to say NAD+
universally decreases with age.
Regardless, the proof
is in the pudding.
What about the second premise
that boosting levels late in life
can improve health and longevity?
We’ll address that question, next.
The effects of NAD+ boosters
on aged rodents
have been described
in the medical literature
as “profound,” “dramatic”…
“remarkable….”
Treated mice had increased
physical activity, improved vision,
and strengthened bones while
delaying or preventing muscle loss,
hearing loss, cognitive decline,
and ovarian aging.
Benefits to nearly every organ
system have been documented,
including improved artery function,
brain function,
heart function,
immune function,
kidney function, liver function,
and muscle function.
For example, a single week of an
NAD+ booster was sufficient
to restore key markers of muscle
health in a 22-month-old mouse
to levels similar to that
of a 6-month-old mouse.
That’s roughly the equivalent
of reverting the muscle health
of a 70-year-old person back
to when they were just 20.
NAD+ boosters can also extend
the lifespans of animals,
presumed to be due to the elevation
of sirtuin activity dependent on NAD+.
This longevity effect
was first demonstrated
more than 20 years
ago in yeast cells.
An overexpression of the genes
involved in NAD+ synthesis
extended replicative lifespans
by as much as 60%.
In the microscopic
worm C. elegans,
NAD+-boosting compounds
have been shown
to extend lifespans
by up to 16%.
In mice, one NAD+ booster
was able to extend lifespan
by a more modest 5%,
but this was accomplished even when
supplementation was started late in life,
which is unusual for
longevity treatments.
No wonder people are excited about
all manner of NAD+ boosting supplements.
The big question is do any of
these healthspan or lifespan effects
translate to benefiting humans?
There are four major NAD+ boosting
supplements on the market these days:
nicotinic acid (NA),
also known as niacin,
nicotinamide (NAM),
also known as niacinamide,
nicotinamide riboside (NR),
and nicotinamide
mononucleotide (NMN).
NAD+ can also be given directly,
as well as its hydrogenated form NADH.
There are also hydrogenated
forms of NMN and NR,
also known as
dihydronicotinamide riboside.
So, there is quite
the alphabet soup:
NA, NAM, NMN, NR, NAD,
NADH, NMNH, and NRH.
The body can also make
NAD+ “from scratch”
from the amino
acid tryptophan.
Given the critical
nature of NAD+,
it is perhaps unsurprising that the
body has so many different pathways
utilizing a panoply
of precursors.
Converting tryptophan to
NAD+ requires eight steps,
whereas NA, NAM, and NR can be turned
into NAD+ in only two or three steps.
NMN is a direct
precursor of NAD+,
but when NMN or NR is taken orally,
it appears to just turn into NA or NAM,
via rapid degradation
in the bloodstream
or active conversion in the liver.
So, why take the more
expensive NMN or NR
if it’s just going to end
up as NA or NAM?
Bought in bulk, NA or NAM
would just cost pennies a day
versus more like a dollar
a day for NR or NMN.
That would add up to hundreds
of dollars a year for NR or NMN
compared to closer to only five bucks
for a whole year’s worth of NA or NAM.
But cost aside, what are the risks
and benefits of all these NAD boosters?
That’s exactly what I’ll cover, next.
The name nicotinic acid was
changed to niacin in the 1940s
to avoid any confusion
with nicotine.
Either name has to be better
than the original moniker, though:
vitamin PP
(for pellagra preventing).
In the 1950s, NA became the world’s
first cholesterol-lowering drug.
This led to more than 20 trials involving
tens of thousands of individuals
taking high doses of
NA for up to six years,
resulting in by far the most
robust safety data we have
on any of the NAD+ precursors.
The most striking benefit was found
in the Coronary Drug Project,
a trial carried out in the pre-statin
drug era of the 1960s and 70s.
The 15-year follow-up found that
those who had been randomized
to years of high-dose NA ended up
with a 6.2% drop in absolute mortality
(52% had died in the NA group
versus 58% in the placebo group).
This sparked major clinical trials that,
sadly, failed so spectacularly
that one was even
stopped prematurely.
All in all, a Cochrane meta-
analysis concluded that
“no evidence of benefits from
niacin therapy” was found.
One possible explanation
for the contrasting results
is that the early promising trials
used immediate release niacin,
while the newer failed trials
used slow release formulations
(also known as extended
or sustained release).
At high doses, regular niacin commonly
causes an intense flushing redness
and prickly heat sensation similar
to a menopausal hot flash.
A slow release version was developed
to reduce this flushing reaction,
catapulting it into a billion-
dollar blockbuster drug,
but it simply doesn’t work as
well to lower cholesterol.
The major clinical trial failures led
to the withdrawal of the drug in Europe
and the removal from
U.S. clinical guidelines
for cardiovascular
disease prevention.
There still may be a role
for niacin preparations
in the treatment
of heart disease
among patients who cannot
tolerate statin drugs,
but what about use for the
general public as an NAD+ booster?
There is a series of
rare genetic defects
that can lead to a condition
called mitochondrial myopathy
that’s characterized by low NAD+
levels in the blood and muscles.
In 2020, researchers demonstrated
that these levels could be repleted
with 750 to 1,000 mg
a day of NA,
which led to a significant
improvement in muscle strength.
This was the first and only study to show
improvements in muscle NAD+ levels
and performance with
any sort of NAD+ booster.
In a control group of individuals
without the genetic defect,
blood levels of NAD+
were raised by NA,
but not muscle levels,
suggesting that NAD+ levels are
already “topped off” in normal muscles.
As you’ll see, this is a recurring
theme among NAD+ boosters.
We know that large doses of NA
can boost NAD+ levels in human blood,
but a corresponding increase in sirtuin
activity has yet to be demonstrated.
Why not give it a try?
Because of the side effects unearthed
in the cholesterol-lowering trials.
NA raises blood sugars and may increase
your risk of developing diabetes.
Based on studies of tens of thousands
of people on high-dose NA
who were followed for years,
one would expect that 1 in 43
people taking NA for five years
would develop diabetes who
otherwise wouldn’t have.
It’s unclear if this risk is only limited
to slow release formulations.
The safety buffer, the ratio between
the tolerable upper limit and the RDA,
is the lowest for NA compared to
half a dozen other common vitamins.
However, the upper limit is just
based on the flushing reaction,
which although uncomfortable,
is considered harmless
and tends to dissipate over time.
Long-term use can have other
adverse consequences, though,
including stomach ulcers,
vomiting, abdominal pain,
diarrhea, and jaundice,
a sign of liver toxicity,
which is worse with
slow-release formulations.
There is also a theoretical concern
that excessive NA intake
may contribute to the development
of Parkinson’s disease.
Due to the unpleasant flushing and
risk of more serious side effects,
interest has moved towards
other NAD+ enhancers.
Ever since nicotinamide (NAM)
was also shown to cure pellagra,
both nicotinic acid, NA, and NAM have been
collectively referred to as niacin or vitamin B3,
though they are
distinct compounds.
For example, NAM is not plagued by
the same kind of hot flash reaction.
(Facial flushing attributed to
niacinamide in some older studies
was likely due to a less purified
form contaminated with residual NA.)
The relative capacity of NA versus
NAM to generate NAD+ is unclear.
Neither has been shown
to boost sirtuin activity,
but both do extend the
lifespan of C. elegans.
I couldn’t find any longevity
trials for NA in rodents;
however, NAM was put to the test
and failed to prolong the lives of mice.
What clinical effects might
we expect in people?
Previously, I explored the proven anti-
aging effects for topical nicotinamide
on the skin and the remarkable ability of
oral nicotinamide to help prevent skin cancer.
I also noted it failed to
prevent type 1 diabetes,
despite promising mouse data,
though it may help preserve
residual function in people
newly diagnosed with
type 1 diabetes,
but apparently not enough
to affect blood sugar control.
What about its use
as a NAD+ booster?
In those with
mitochondrial myopathy,
NA raised muscle NAD+ levels and
improved mitochondrial and muscle function,
but in healthy individuals,
muscle NAD+ levels didn’t budge.
However, the average age of individuals
in the control group was 50.
What about in older adults whose muscle
NAD+ levels might potentially be lower?
Four NAD+ precursors were tested
in older adults averaging in their 70s:
tryptophan, NA, NAM, and NR.
All four failed to improve
muscle strength or function,
failed to affect mitochondrial function,
and failed to even nudge
NAD+ levels in their muscles.
Why not give it a try anyway?
Again, side effects.
Like NA, high-dose NAM can cause
gastrointestinal disturbances
and signs of liver toxicity….
However, NAM may result in more
issues involving methylation.
The first step in breaking down excess
NAM is to transfer a methyl group to it,
forming methylnicotinamide.
Unfortunately,
methylnicotinamide is neurotoxic
and can cross the
blood-brain barrier.
This may explain why NAM can exacerbate
Parkinson’s-like symptoms in rats
and why Parkinson’s patients
have higher levels
of the NAM-methylating
enzyme in their brains.
And the same with Alzheimer's
brains for that matter.
Excess NAM may also deplete
the body’s pool of methyl groups.
If you read the Epigenetics chapter
in my book How Not to Age,
you may remember that DNA methylation is
critical for the regulation of gene expression.
Epigenetic changes caused by
NAM-induced methyl depletion
have been blamed as the reason
why rats fed megadoses of NAM
suffer from fatty livers
and swollen kidneys,
but that was at a human-equivalent dose
far exceeding what people might take.
Is there any evidence that
more modest NAM supplementation
might affect methylation in humans?
Yes, and even with a single
dose as low as 100 mg.
Methylation also plays a key role in
breaking down fight-or-flight hormones
like noradrenaline and neurotransmitters
like serotonin and histamine.
Within hours of a single
100 mg dose of NAM,
blood levels of all three
become elevated,
suggesting their metabolism was impaired
by the shunting of methyl groups
to deal with the excess NAM.
Also noted was a significant
rise in homocysteine,
which is a byproduct of
methylation reactions
and a risk factor for cardiovascular
disease and dementia.
Another potential problem with NAM
is that it’s a sirtuin inhibitor.
Wait, I thought the whole purpose of taking
NAD+ precursors is to boost sirtuin activity.
Sirtuin enzymes use up
NAD+ and spit out NAM.
This allows the body to recycle the NAM
back into NAD+ for further sirtuin use.
But it also means the body can use
NAM as part of a negative feedback loop.
Like a thermostat in the winter
that shuts down the furnace
when there’s too much heat,
the body shuts down NAD+ use by
sirtuins when it detects too much NAM.
NAM pills didn’t exist
when our bodies evolved;
so, in the wake of a
sudden wave of NAM,
the body must think its sirtuins are
churning out too much and dials them back.
Perhaps, this explains why NAM
fails to prolong the lifespans of mice.
When the sirtuin-suppressing effects of
NAM were first reported 20 years ago,
the researchers cautioned that
this could potentially lead to
“deleterious consequences of long-term
nicotinamide therapy in humans.”
NR and NMN seem to be more promising
NAD+ precursors than NA or NAM,
since they don’t cause flushing
nor do they directly inhibit sirtuins.
In mice, NR and NMN both
raised liver NAD+ levels,
but of the two, only NR significantly
raised NAD+ in the muscles.
Also, NR is so far the only NAD+ booster
shown to prolong the lifespan of mice.
There have been at least
10 clinical trials of NR,
most showing it can boost human
blood levels of NAD+ by up to 168%.
Note, though, that most doses
used exceeded 300 mg,
which is the daily dose
approved as safe
by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration
and European Food Safety Authority.
At the approved dose, blood NAD+ is
boosted more on the order of 50 to 60%,
but no dose was found to affect NAD+ levels
in human muscle (compared to placebo).
The greater preponderance
of human bioavailability
and safety data for
NR compared to NMN
has led some to proclaim NR
as the preferred NAD+ precursor.
And, by some, I mean employees
of a chemical company
that produces NR for supplements.
The question after all
of these human NR trials
is have any of them
shown clinical benefit?
Sadly, no.
Let’s go through the alphabet.
After accounting for
multiple testing,
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials of NR
in middle-aged or older adults failed to find
any significant benefit over placebo
for artery stiffness or
artery function, BAT activation,
blood pressure, blood sugar control,
body weight,
cardiac energy or ejection fraction,
fat burning,
fatty liver, exercise capacity,
fatigue,
insulin sensitivity,
metabolic flexibility,
metabolic health,
metabolic rate,
mitochondrial function
or biogenesis,
muscle blood flow, upper
or lower body muscle strength,
pancreatic function or the
release of metabolic hormones,
the treatment of Parkinson’s disease
symptoms, or physical performance.
NR-hawking companies claim
NR is anti-inflammatory,
but in their own study, only 3 out of 10
markers of inflammation were affected
compared to placebo,
and a subsequent independent study
using the same dose for twice as long
found zero of 12 markers affected.
Remarkably, the opposite was found for
many of these outcomes in rats and mice.
In rodents, NR does raise
NAD+ levels in muscle,
improving insulin sensitivity
and mitochondrial biogenesis,
and on down much of the list.
Why does NR work in rodents but
appear to almost entirely flop in people?
Some have suggested
inadequate dosing.
The typical dose used
in mouse studies
Was about twice that used
in many human studies,
but a double dose has been
tried in people, to no avail.
Another possibility is sirtuin inhibition by NAM,
the main degradation product of NR.
In fact, based on mouse studies,
NR may metabolize in the gut into NAM or
NA before it even makes it in the bloodstream.
Either way, unlike in mice,
NR can’t seem to elevate
NAD+ in human muscle;
so, no wonder there’s no alteration
of human sirtuin activity.
Maybe that explains
the disparate results.
In fact, the key NAD+ synthesizing
enzyme in human muscle biopsies
was actually suppressed
by NR supplementation.
This doesn’t happen in mice,
but it does in people.
Presumably this downregulation
is an adaptive response
to the unnaturally large flood
of NR coming into the system.
So, what happens when you
stop taking the supplement?
How quickly does your enzyme
activity bounce back?
In mice, not only may
their microbiome affect NR,
but the NR may affect
their microbiome, too.
Some of the benefits of NR
can then be transferred
between mice via
fecal transplants.
So, at least in mice,
some of the benefits of NR
may be due to modulating
the mouse microbiome.
The distinct differences between the
gut flora of humans and rodents
may offer another explanation why
NR works in them, but not us.
Unlike NAM, supplementation with
NR did not increase homocysteine levels,
but one study of a combination of NR
plus a resveratrol analogue called pterostilbene
raised LDL cholesterol high enough to kill
as many as 1 in 40 long-term users.
However, this effect is presumed
to be due to the pterostilbene,
as NR alone has not been shown to raise LDL,
whereas pterostilbene has.
One study did find that NR seems to
cause a small reduction in hematocrit,
hemoglobin, and platelet count in
people within a week of starting it.
This shift towards a
more anemic state
was suggested to account for impaired
exercise performance seen in rats given NR.
However, the 35% drop in performance
did not reach statistical significance.
NR did cause a significant increase
in systemic oxidative stress, however,
and another rodent study
found a worsening of inflammation
and deterioration of
metabolic health,
but if positive effects in rodents
don’t translate to people,
perhaps we shouldn’t expect
that negative ones will either.
Regulatory authorities
from Australia, Canada,
Europe, and the United States
have all authorized NR as safe,
at least up to 300mg a day
(or 230 in pregnant and lactating women).
But the lack of demonstrable clinical benefit
would seem to preclude NR supplementation.
Both NR and NMN have been shown
to have beneficial effects in rodents,
though they haven’t
been tested side-by-side.
Both precursors raise blood
levels of NAD+ in people
but similarly haven’t been pitted
head-to-head against one another.
One potential advantage
of NMN over NR
is that it may be more
stable in the bloodstream.
In mouse blood at least, within an hour,
most NR is converted into NAM,
whereas NMN levels remain steady.
You could also argue that NMN is better
because it’s a direct precursor of NAD+,
whereas NR first has
to be converted to NMN;
so, we might as well just
take NMN in the first place.
Ironically, the exact opposite
argument can also be made
based on the inability of NMN to
pass through cell membranes.
Structurally, NMN is just NR with
a phosphate group attached to it.
The phosphate charge prevents NMN
from passing in and out of cells;
so, to get inside a cell, NMN first
has to be converted into NR.
Then, once inside, the NR can turn
back into NMN and make NAD+.
So, if NMN first has to be converted
into NR for cell entry, the argument goes,
maybe you might as well
just take NR to begin with,
because there’s no
NMN transporter.
Or is there?
An NMN transporter was recently
described (at least in mouse intestine);
so, maybe NMN is
able to skip the NR step
and pass directly into cells
to make NAD+ after all.
However, the evidence that such a NMN
transporter exists remains controversial.
NMN boasts a long list of
rodent healthspan benefits,
but, unlike NR, has yet to demonstrate
an extension of mammalian lifespan.
What about in people?
There have just been a few human
NMN studies published to date.
One small study of healthy
middle-aged men
found that various single doses
had no apparent effect
on any of the measured variables,
including retinal eye function,
sleep quality, heart rate,
blood pressure,
oxygenation,
or body temperature.
A 12-week study of daily NMN supplementation
in middle-aged men and women
similarly found no significant
effects on any outcome,
including lean mass,
muscle mass, body fat,
blood sugars, cholesterol,
or insulin sensitivity.
NMN did boost blood NAD+ levels,
though they peaked after the first month
and then trended down
for months two and three;
so, there may have been an
adaptive drop in NAD+ synthesis
as was suspected with NR.
Like NR, NMN also fails to
raise NAD+ in muscle tissue.
One study evocatively entitled,
“Nicotinamide Mononucleotide Supplementation
Enhances Aerobic Capacity in Amateur Runners,”
tested three different doses of
NMN versus placebo for six weeks
among young and middle-
aged recreational runners.
Aerobic capacity was increased at one
ventilatory threshold, but not the other.
No overall benefit for aerobic
capacity or peak power
or any of another ten measures of
cardiopulmonary function was found.
If you measure enough things,
statistical outliers,
both positive and negative ones,
can just pop up as flukes.
For example, the researchers
noted significant improvement
in the single-leg stance test,
but the NMN had no significant effect on
any of the other physical function tests.
And upon closer inspection,
the apparent single-leg balance benefit
was only found in the middle-dose group
compared to the high-dose group,
because the high-dose group ended up
doing slightly worse compared to baseline.
No significant effect was found for
any of the doses compared to placebo.
A similar issue can be found in a 12-week
study of NMN supplementation in older adults.
The NMN company-funded
authors concluded
that NMN “improved lower limb function
and reduced drowsiness in older adults.”
But it failed to significantly
affect 16 additional measures,
including other tests of lower
limb function and fatigue.
There are so few NMN studies that this
kind of shotgun approach is understandable,
casting the widest possible net
for effects to be further tested,
but on their own cannot be presented
as convincing proof of efficacy.
All of the above NMN studies
were on healthy individuals.
What about testing NMN on those who
are already metabolically compromised?
Overweight or obese postmenopausal
women with prediabetes
were randomized to NMN
or placebo for 10 weeks.
NMN didn’t seem to affect
body weight or composition,
liver fat, blood pressure,
or a dozen other metabolic variables,
but it did improve
muscle insulin sensitivity,
though not enough to affect insulin levels
or short- or long-term blood sugar control.
This may be because insulin sensitivity
in the liver and body fat remained unchanged.
NMN also appeared to have no
effect on mitochondrial function
or muscle strength,
fatigability, or recovery.
In terms of safety, NMN shills speak of it as
being naturally found in fruits and vegetables,
but even the most concentrated sources
(edamame, avocado, and broccoli)
have over a hundred times less per serving
than the typical NMN supplement dose.
The same could be said for NR in milk
(human and otherwise).
There are safety evaluations for NMN
on rats and dogs, but unlike NR,
supplemental doses of NMN have yet to
be shown as safe for human consumption.
There are rodent studies
showing that NMN
may have negative metabolic
consequences compared to placebo,
but the most serious concern
is nerve degeneration.
The accumulation of NMN
in nerve cells is toxic.
Since NR is converted into NMN,
this is a major concern for
NR supplementation as well.
The type of nerve damage,
axon degeneration,
is a major contributor to a variety
of neurodegenerative disorders.
Blocking an NMN-synthesizing enzyme
appeared to help damaged neurons in vitro,
protection that’s abolished
by adding NMN back,
and adding an enzyme that chews up
NMN was also found to be protective,
further supporting a theory of degenerative
effects of accumulating NMN.
However, clinical effects
remain theoretical,
as these adverse effects have only been
demonstrated in fish, mice, and petri dishes.
Of course, NMN supplements may not
even have NMN in the first place.
ChromaDex, which sells the rival
supplement Tru Niagen (a form of NR),
claims to have tested the 22 NMN brands
with the highest market share on Amazon
and found that most had
virtually no NMN at all.
Ironically, many of the apparently fake
NMN products displayed quote-unquote
“certificates of analysis” and carried
hundreds or thousands of positive reviews.
Evidently, only 3 out of 22 were found to contain
as much NMN as advertised on their label.
Of course, ChromaDex isn’t
above being shady itself;
it’s been accused of making
hyped false claims for Tru Niagen
by both the FDA and the
Better Business Bureau.
In short, NR has been demonstrated
to be relatively safe but not effective,
and neither safety nor efficacy
has been established for NMN.
Taking niacin,
also called nicotinic acid,
would be about 50 times
more efficient
than taking
the amino acid tryptophan
to boost NAD+,
because only about two percent
of tryptophan
is converted into niacin.
Also, tryptophan didn't work
to improve mitochondrial
or muscle function
in physically compromised
older adults,
even when combined
with niacin or nicotinamide.
And side effects
of taking tryptophan
include belching and gas,
blurred vision,
diarrhea, dizziness,
drowsiness, dry mouth,
headache, heartburn,
and potentially
a life-threatening condition
known as eosinophilia-myalgia
syndrome, or EMS.
There was an epidemic of EMS
tied to tryptophan supplements
from a single supplier
back in 1989
that led to their removal
from the market
for about 15 years.
Some sort of contaminant
was suspected,
but the cause
remains a mystery.
To this day,
tryptophan supplements
continue to be tainted
with impurities,
with at least one case
of EMS reported
decades after
the initial epidemic.
A case of EMS tied to
a bizarre weight loss diet
involving hundreds of cups
(~48 L) of cashews,
a rich source of tryptophan,
suggests the syndrome
can be caused
by excess tryptophan directly.
If anything,
tryptophan restriction
may be beneficial.
Nearly 50 years ago,
it was demonstrated
that restricting
dietary tryptophan
reduced cancer rates
and increased
the lifespans of rats
and, subsequently, mice.
Vegetarians and vegans
both appear to have
significantly lower intakes
of tryptophan,
but only in vegans
does this translate
to lower
tryptophan blood levels,
though presumably not
if they were to take
tryptophan supplements.
What about taking NAD+ directly?
This isn't practical
because of instability
and poor bioavailability.
NAD+ is vulnerable to heat,
pH, light, and oxygen,
requiring dark desiccant storage
at ideally 20 degrees (-29°C)
below freezing.
NAD+ can be given intravenously,
a practice started
in the 1950s
as an "underground" treatment
for alcoholism,
but when taken orally,
NAD may be broken down
in the alkaline environment
of the small intestine,
and NADH,
the so-called "reduced" form
of NAD+,
is broken down
in the acidic conditions
of the stomach.
(In organic chemistry,
the gain of a hydrogen atom
is said to quote-unquote
"reduce" the molecule,
so NADH
is the reduced form of NAD+).
Enteric forms of NAD+
could potentially survive
the digestive tract, but,
with the exception of neurons,
NAD can't cross
into mammalian cells.
This is why
NAD+ precursor supplements,
like NMN and NR,
were developed.
Also, there are evidently
(unpublished) data
showing that straight NAD+
can cause severe hyperglycemia
in mice.
Has it been tested in people?
NAD+ boosting supplements
have been found
to improve the learning
and memory of rodent models
of Alzheimer's disease
in the lab.
In 1995, case reports
of apparent benefit of NADH
for Alzheimer's disease
were published.
By the next year, an open-label
pilot study was published,
suggesting it had
a protective effect,
but without
a placebo control group,
the only conclusion
that could be drawn
was to study it further,
especially since
a similar study
with the same dose
over approximately
the same period
found no evidence
of any cognitive effects.
There have been
two randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials
of NAD precursors
for Alzheimer's.
One found no benefit
for memory, attention,
or clinician ratings
of dementia severity,
but did maybe find
less of a drop
in one dementia rating scale
after six months
of 10 milligrams a day of NADH.
The other, a six-month study
of nicotinamide,
failed to find
any clinical effects.
What about trying
NMNH and NRH,
the reduced forms
of NMN and NR?
They both appear
to boost NAD+ higher
than their
non-reduced counterparts.
In vitro,
NMNH can raise NAD+ levels
up to 10 times higher than NMN,
and NRH (also known as
dihydronicotinamide riboside)
is up to about 50 times
more potent than NR.
There are concerns
about stability of NRH
outside the body,
since it's sensitive to oxygen
and moisture,
but within the body,
NRH may be more stable,
not rapidly devolving
into nicotinamide,
like NR does
(at least in mouse blood).
However, unlike NR,
NRH does not appear
to be able
to significantly increase levels
in mouse muscles.
NRH is said to have
a "spectacular potency"
for increasing NAD+ levels,
perhaps the most potent
precursor discovered to date.
This may not necessarily be
a good thing.
The extreme boost
afforded by NRH
had detrimental consequences
in human liver cells in vitro,
resulting from
an excessive accumulation
of free radicals.
In addition to oxidation,
NRH was also found
promote inflammation.
Pro-inflammatory effects
were noted for NRH
on human immune cells in vitro
(but not for NMN, NAM, or NR).
Because it appears that NMNH
is converted to NRH
to enter cells,
these potentially
deleterious effects
may be shared
by NMNH as well
(though this has yet
to be tested).
Most of the reported
side effects
for NAD+ precursors,
like NAM, NR, and NMN,
are relatively rare and minor,
for example, diarrhea,
nausea, rashes, hot flashes,
and leg cramps.
Both NR and NMN
raise NAM levels,
so may share
in the same concerns
regarding sirtuin inhibition,
methyl depletion,
and potential adverse effects
of NAM breakdown products.
Another theoretical concern
of NAD+ boosting
is the exacerbation
of infections
by a group of bacteria
called Haemophilus
(from the Greek
meaning "blood loving,"
though can also cause
infections of the lungs,
brain, throat,
flesh, and joints).
Haemophilus bacteria lack
the ability to make NAD+,
so rely on host levels,
raising the possibility
that higher blood levels
might worsen the disease course
of infected individuals.
Ironically,
elevated NAD+ levels
may also fuel
immune system overreaction
in cases of auto-immune
and inflammatory disease.
When fully activated,
the immune system is voracious.
The immune reaction
to a blood infection
or extensive burns can burn
4,000 calories a day,
approximating military training
in the Arctic.
Since NAD+ is used by cells
to produce energy,
it's no surprise that we find
the primary NAD+
synthesizing enzyme
strongly upregulated
in tissues
that are actively inflamed.
For example,
the enzyme NAMPT is elevated
in colonoscopy biopsies
taken from inflamed areas
in patients with
inflammatory bowel disease,
and higher levels
are correlated
with greater disease severity.
So, for those suffering from
chronic autoimmune diseases,
such as rheumatoid arthritis,
NAD+ boosting
could potentially have
a "profound negative impact."
This explains
why tamping down NAD+
with NAMPT inhibitors
has been shown
to ameliorate colitis
and arthritis in mice,
but this has yet
to be tested in people.
Such NAD+ depleting drugs
have, however,
been used in cancer patients.
Malignancy is another heavily
energy-consuming process.
NAD+ may, therefore,
have a tumor-promoting effect
by promoting cancer cell growth
and spread.
For example, NAMPT,
the NAD+-forming enzyme,
is highly expressed
in cancerous brain tumors
and correlates with
decreased patient survival.
This has led to attempts
to use NAD+-depleting therapies
to try to starve
cancer progression,
but this approach is confounded
by rapid onset injury
to another
energy-intensive tissue,
the retina,
risking blindness.
Giving NMN to mice
with pancreatic cancer
accelerates the progression
of the cancer,
thought due to the aggravation
of inflammation.
The researchers conclude that
consumers of NAD+ supplements
must "balance the advantageous
anti-ageing effects
with the potential detrimental
pro-tumorigenic side effects."
Perhaps this explains
why the best NAD+ boosters
have ever been able to do
is increase mice lifespan
by five percent.
On the other hand,
as you'll remember,
NAM successfully prevented
human skin cancers
and has been found
to reduce the incidence
of a variety
of carcinogen-induced tumors
in rodents.
The disparate results
may in part be due
to the disparate impact
sirtuin activation
may have on different cancers.
Sirtuin activity
can be overexpressed
in some cancers
(like thyroid carcinomas
and lung metastasis)
but reduced in others
(like brain, bladder, prostate,
and ovarian tumors).
The bottom line
is that particular caution
should be used
for NAD+-boosting supplements
by those with cancer,
or a personal or strong
family history of cancer,
and perhaps also by those
with inflammatory disorders
and certain active infections.
So, which NAD+ boosting
supplement is best?
There’s no clear standout,
as hardly any of the preclinical
effects found in the lab
have translated into evidence
of human clinical benefit.
Perhaps, this failure is to be expected
given the complexity of NAD+ physiology,
with its juggling of multiple precursors,
production pathways, and recycling routes.
The bottom line is that it’s just too early
to say if NAD+ booster supplementation
will ever live up to even
a fraction of the hype.
Many more, larger, and longer-term studies
are necessary to establish safety and efficacy.
The problem is that because NA, NAM,
NR, and NMN are all natural products,
they can’t be patented;
so, the money for well-designed
clinical trials is not as available.
The reason there have been comparatively
more trials done on NR than NMN
is that patents were originally issued for NR
before being invalidated as unpatentable.
Perhaps blindly overloading the
system with NAD+ precursors
is not the best way to go
about NAD+ restoration.
The body seems too smart to allow such
blunt incursion to affect tissue levels.
Maybe these supplements are
just profit-making distractions
from more natural approaches.
Broadly, there are three main
ways to increase NAD+ levels.
Increasing the supply of NAD+
precursors is just the first.
The other two are having
the body make more,
by activating NAD+
synthesizing enzymes,
or have the body use less, via an
inhibition of excess NAD+ degradation.
The primary determinant of NAD+
synthesis in the enzyme NAMPT.
An abundance of NAMPT tends to
decrease with age in human muscle,
dropping steadily by about 40%
between the ages of 20 and 80.
In our liver, it drops by half.
However, age-related diseases,
such as atherosclerosis,
cancer, diabetes,
and rheumatoid arthritis,
have been found to exacerbate
NAMPT decline,
raising a chicken or
the egg question.
There’s where interventional
trials come in.
Similar NAMPT declines have been
noted in aging rats and mice.
Does boosting NAMPT help?
Increasing NAMPT or its species
equivalent increases the lifespans
of yeast, fruit flies, and rodents.
An NAMPT boost also increases aerobic
capacity and exercise endurance in mice,
in addition to helping them live longer.
Enhanced expression of NAMPT increases
the NAD+ levels in the muscles in mice
comparable to feeding them
dietary NAD+ precursors,
but if you remember,
NAD+ precursors don’t seem to be able to
affect NAD+ muscle levels in most people.
In fact, such supplements can
actually suppress NAMPT,
while boosting that methylating enzyme
to rid the body of the excess.
In addition to methyl depletion,
chronic administration
of these supplements
could potentially then leave people
worse off should they ever stop them.
There is, however, a way to naturally
boost NAMPT and NAD+ levels in humans
without any supplements: exercise.
Athletes have about twice the NAMPT
expression in their musculature
compared to sedentary individuals.
To prove cause and effect,
sedentary men and women started
a stationary bike exercise protocol,
and within three weeks, NAMPT
levels increased by 127%.
Resistance training can
also increase NAMPT,
and this can also translate into a
127% increase in muscle NAD+ levels
and a rise in sirtuin activity.
In other words,
exercise can do what NAD+
boosting supplements can’t.
There are three
NAD+ boosting strategies:
Increasing the supply
of NAD+ precursors
is just one way.
The other two
are having the body make more,
by activating
NAD+-synthesizing enzymes,
or have the body use less,
by, for example,
conserving it, by using less.
Besides sirtuins,
the major consumers
of NAD+ are PARP-1 and CD38.
PARP-1 is an enzyme
that uses NAD+ to repair DNA.
The more oxidative DNA damage,
the more single
and double stranded DNA breaks,
the more enzymes like PARP-1
need to be activated
to come to the rescue.
This uses up a lot of NAD.
As DNA damage
accumulates with age,
the rising need
for repair enzymes like PARP-1
causes a major drain
on NAD+ levels.
Exposing cells in vitro
to DNA damaging agents,
such as gamma radiation
or genotoxic chemicals,
can cause an 80
to 90 percent drop
in NAD+ levels
within a matter of minutes.
This has led to the search
for PARP-1 blockers
to preserve NAD+ levels,
but rather than blocking
DNA repair,
why not work to prevent
so much damage
in the first place?
For example,
the severe oxidative stress
of a high-fat diet
can lead to PARP-1 activation
and NAD+ depletion in mice,
but NAD+ levels can be
"dramatically restored"
by feeding them
"purple sweet potato color,"
the natural
anthocyanin pigments
found in purple sweet potatoes.
Or, of course, you can just not
feed them a high-fat diet.
DNA repair is a good thing.
PARP-1 may be
one of the reasons
NAD+-boosting interventions
can improve healthspans
and lifespans
in laboratory animals.
Greater PARP activity
strongly correlates
with longer lifespan
across about a dozen
mammalian species,
and the PARP activity
of human centenarians
averages 60 percent higher
than younger controls.
However, persistent activation
can lead to NAD+ depletion,
and overactivation
can lead to cell death.
So, we should try to keep
oxidative stress to a minimum.
CD38 is another major guzzler
of NAD+.
It's an enzyme that uses NAD+
found concentrated
on the surfaces
of immune cells
and robustly induced
in the context of inflammation.
The rise of CD38 activity
with age
has been blamed on persistent
"inflammaging" activation,
the rise in systemic low-grade
inflammation in our bodies
when we get older,
which may be a major culprit
for falling NAD+ levels.
For example, blocking CD38
has been found
to raise NAD+ levels
in old mice
comparable to that
of younger mice.
So, oxidation and inflammation
can lead to a drop
in NAD+ levels,
due to the excess activation
of the NAD+ consuming enzymes.
This may explain why
protective sirtuin activity
is reduced in obesity,
a condition characterized
by oxidative stress
and inflammation.
A study of identical twin pairs
in which one, on average,
was obese and the other not,
found significantly
less sirtuin expression
in the obese twin,
despite having
the same genetics.
And randomize people
to a six-month trial
of 25 percent
calorie restriction,
and you can show a boost
in sirtuin expression
along with a decrease
in DNA damage.
Protein restriction
may have a similar effect,
since men and women
with higher protein intake
tend to have lower levels
of NAD+ in their blood,
thought to be due
to the oxidative stress
induced by protein
breakdown byproducts.
If oxidation and inflammation
are responsible
for a drop in NAD+ levels,
then what about the antioxidant
and anti-inflammatory
phytonutrients
in healthy plant foods?
After screening
more than 14,000 compounds,
almost all flavonoids
were found to be effective
in a test for CD38 inhibition.
The two most effective
were cyanidin,
found in red cabbage
and blackberries,
and quercetagetin,
found in marigold flower tea.
Another study found
the three most potent compounds
were luteolin, kuromanin,
and luteolinidin.
Luteolin is found concentrated
in oregano, radicchio,
and chrysanthemum tea.
Kuromanin is found
in black berries, purple corn,
and hibiscus tea.
Corn tortillas are
surprisingly easy to make;
so why not choose blue
or purple masa
to make them even healthier?
Luteolinidin,
found to increase NAD+
in the hearts of rats,
can be found in red sorghum,
one of the components
of my prebiotic BROL mix,
when I can find it.
The flavonoid apigenin
is a well-established
CD38 inhibitor.
When given to mice,
apigenin boosts NAD+ levels
by about 50 percent,
which is what people would get
taking the maximum
tolerable daily dose of NR.
The best sources are parsley
and chamomile tea.
A wide range of flavonoids
found in green tea, turmeric,
and fruits and vegetables
have also been found
to prevent NAD+ depletion
in human cells in vitro
at levels found in the blood
after consumption.
How much do you have to eat,
though?
Proanthocyanidins have been
found to lower PARP-1
and CD38 expression in rats.
NAD+ and sirtuin activity
was significantly boosted
at the human equivalent dose
of about 280 milligrams a day.
How much is that?
That's the amount
of proanthocyanidins
found in a single apple.
You could also reach that dose
eating two plums,
a half cup of wild blueberries,
a little over a teaspoon
of cinnamon,
or a little over a tablespoon,
like four teaspoons,
of cocoa powder.
Quercetin is another suppressor
of PARP-1 and CD38
shown to increase
sirtuin activity in mice.
The concentration necessary
to lower PARP-1 in vitro
can be achieved by taking
a quercetin supplement,
but typical supplement
manufacturers'
recommended doses
are up to 100 times
the average daily
dietary intake.
Thankfully, food works too.
Researchers fried up
one and a half yellow onions
and raised
quercetin blood levels
to about 75 percent there.
And so, two onions might do it.
There's no long-term
safety data
on high-dose
flavonoid supplementation;
so, public health researchers
suggest
"caution should be exercised
in ingesting them
at levels above which
would be obtained
from a typical
vegetarian diet."